<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two orders of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament: concerning a committee of citizens, chosen and appointed by the Parliament to see that no gun powder be conveyed out of London, without speciall warrant from them, the Lord Generall, or both Houses of Parliament. Also authorizing them to search and examine what quantities of gun-powder is, or shall be in the hands of any merchants, grocers, or any others, within the City of London, and 20 miles about, and to sirze [sic] upon whatsoever shall be found, for use of the Parliament. Likewise to issue out warrants to such persons as they shall thinke fit, to search by land or water all suspitious carriages, packs, trunks, or other things wherein gun-powder may be probably carried, and to sieze upon all they so find. With the names of the said committee of citizens. Die Sabbathi, Decemb. 3. 1642. Ordered by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, that these two orders bee forthwith printed and published. Iohn Browne Cler. Parl.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83539</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871447</idno>
  <idno type="VID">156267</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240945058</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E129_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21544</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871447</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99871447e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83539)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156267)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 23:E129[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two orders of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament: concerning a committee of citizens, chosen and appointed by the Parliament to see that no gun powder be conveyed out of London, without speciall warrant from them, the Lord Generall, or both Houses of Parliament. Also authorizing them to search and examine what quantities of gun-powder is, or shall be in the hands of any merchants, grocers, or any others, within the City of London, and 20 miles about, and to sirze [sic] upon whatsoever shall be found, for use of the Parliament. Likewise to issue out warrants to such persons as they shall thinke fit, to search by land or water all suspitious carriages, packs, trunks, or other things wherein gun-powder may be probably carried, and to sieze upon all they so find. With the names of the said committee of citizens. Die Sabbathi, Decemb. 3. 1642. Ordered by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, that these two orders bee forthwith printed and published. Iohn Browne Cler. Parl.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Decem. 5. Printed for Iohn Wright in the Old Bailey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Gunpowder --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Equipment and supplies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156267:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156267:1"/>
            <p> TWO ORDERS Of the LORDS and COMMONS Assembled in PARLIAMENT: Concerning a Committee of Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, chosen and appointed by the Parliament to see that no Gun-Powder be conveyed out of <hi>London,</hi> without speciall Warrant from them, the Lord Generall, or both Houses of PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>Also authorizing them to search and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what quantities of Gun-Powder is, or shall be in the hands of any Merchants, Grocers, or any others, within the City of London, and 20 miles about, and to sirze upon whatsoever shall be found, for the use of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Likewise to issue out Warrants to such Persons as they shall thinke fit, to search by Land or Water all suspiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous carriages, Packs, Trunks, or other things wherein Gun-Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may by probably carried, and to sieze upon all they so find.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the names of the said Committee of Citizens.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Sabbathi, Decemb. 3. 1642.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ORdered by the Lords and Commons Assembled in Parliament, that these two Orders bee forthwith Printed and published.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Iohn Browne Cler. Parl.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Decem. 5. Printed for Iohn Wright in the Old Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ley. 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156267:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156267:2"/>
            <head>TVVO ORDERS OF THE Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Die Sabbathi,</hi> 3. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is this day Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the Lords &amp; Commons now assembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssioners of Customes nor any other Officer or servant of the Customhouse within the City of <hi>London,</hi> take any Entries, or passe any Warrants for Gunpowder, to be exported without warrant
<pb facs="tcp:156267:3"/> from the greater part of the Committe of Citizens appointed to take care for that Commodity, and that no Carrier, Waggoner, Watchman, Wharfinger, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther person whatsoever shal carry or convey out, or suffer to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or conveyed out any Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder to any place without warrant from both Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or of the Committe of Lords and Commons for safety of the Kingdome, or of the Lord General, or of the said Committee of Citizens before mentioned; And that all Shipmasters upon their severall returnes from their Voyages, to bring in a true and exact Certificate to the said Committe of Citizens, of the
<pb facs="tcp:156267:3"/> quantity of Gunpowder they shal have remaining of their store car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The names of the Committe of Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens appointed for this service.</head>
               <item>Kichard VVaring.</item>
               <item>Richard Hunt.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Tompson.</item>
               <item>Iohn Lane.</item>
               <item>Thomas Browne Iunior.</item>
               <item>Greensmith.</item>
               <item>Balton.</item>
               <item>Thomas Foote.</item>
               <item>Thomas Brightwel.</item>
               <item>Samuell Langham.</item>
               <item>Samuell Harsnett.</item>
               <item>George Foxcroft.</item>
               <item>Thomas Stock.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156267:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Die Sabbathi,</hi> 3. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is this day Ordered by the Lords and Commons now assembled in Parliament, That <hi>Richard Waring, Thomas Foote, Thomas Brightwell, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell Langham, Samuell Harsnett, George Foxcroft, Thomas Stock, Richard Hunt, VVilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Thompsom, Iohn Lane, Thomas Browne Iunior, Greensmith,</hi> and <hi>Bolton,</hi> Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> shall hereby be Authorized to enquire, search, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, what quantities of Gunpowder is, or shall be in the hands of any Merchants, Ship-chand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Grocers, Societies, or Companies, or any others, as to the persons here before nominated to be a Committee for this service, shall seeme fit within the City of <hi>London,</hi> and twenty miles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the same; As likewise to seize upon whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Gunpowder shall be so found for the use of the Parliament; And to this cause the same to be brought to such Ware-houses, as the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee shall appoynt for which the Owners are to be payd at such reasonable prizes, and at such times as the said Committee of Citizens, or the
<pb facs="tcp:156267:4"/> greater number of them, shall rate and set downe; And that they lay a restraint uppn all persons whatsoever, with whom such Gunpowder shall be found, from selling or conveying away to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny person or persons any quantity of Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, upon any pretence whatsoever, without Order from both Houses of Parliament, or the Lord Generall, or the Committee of Lords and Commons for safety of the Kingdome, or the greater part of the Committee of Citizens for this service. It is further Ordered, that all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and others that import any Gunpowder, shall apply themselves to the said Committee, and not take any Gunpowder out of any Ship, or other Vessell in which it is Imported, without speciall Licence of the said Committee of Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens; To the end, they may have the offer and refusall of the same before it be otherwise dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of, And that the said Committee of Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, shall Issue out Warrants to such persons as they shall thinke fit to search by Land, or Water, all suspitious Carriages, Packs, Trunks, and other Vessells or things wherein Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may probably be carried; And seize, and bring the same Powder to the Ware-houses a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, for the use aforesaid, if the said Powder be conveied or attempted to be conveied away without sufficient Warrant.</p>
            <p>And for the more effectuall performance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is also Ordered, that the said Committee
<pb facs="tcp:156267:5"/> doe often meet together, for the better pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this Order, whereof they are to give an account weekely, to the Committee of Lords and Commons for safety of the Kingdome; And that all Charges incident to this service, shall be payd by Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerrard,</hi> Treasurer of the Armie, the charges being first allowed and certified by the greater part of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, hereby Authorized to doe this ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>